<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  
   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
-->

<document url="webapp.html">

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <title>The Webapp Connector</title>
  </properties>

<body>


<section name="Introduction">

  <p><b>IMPORTANT NOTE: The Webapp connector is now deprecated. Use the 
  <a href="coyotejk.html">Coyote JK Connector</a> with
  <a href="jk.html">JK</a> or
  <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs-2.1/mod/mod_proxy_ajp.html">
  mod_proxy_ajp</a> instead.</b></p>

  <p>The <strong>Webapp Connector</strong> element represents a
  <strong>Connector</strong> component that communicates with a web
  connector via the <code>WARP</code> protocol.  This is used for cases
  where you wish to invisibly integrate Tomcat 4 into an existing (or new)
  Apache installation, and you want Apache to handle the static content
  contained in the web application, and/or utilize Apache's SSL
  processing.  In many application environments, this will result in
  better overall performance than running your applications under
  Tomcat stand-alone using the
  <a href="http11.html">HTTP/1.1 Connector</a>. However, the only way
  to know for sure whether it will provide better performance for
  <strong>your</strong> application is to try it both ways.</p>

  <p><strong>FIXME</strong> - general description of what happens at server
  startup time when you have the WARP Connector configured.</p>

</section>


<section name="Attributes">

  <subsection name="Common Attributes">

  <p>All implementations of <strong>Connector</strong>
  support the following attributes:</p>

  <attributes>

    <attribute name="className" required="true">
      <p>Java class name of the implementation to use.  This class must
      implement the <code>org.apache.catalina.Connector</code> interface.
      You must specify the standard value defined below.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="enableLookups" required="false">
      <p>Set to <code>true</code> if you want calls to
      <code>request.getRemoteHost()</code> to perform DNS lookups in
      order to return the actual host name of the remote client.  Set
      to <code>false</code> to skip the DNS lookup and return the IP
      address in String form instead (thereby improving performance).
      By default, DNS lookups are disabled.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="redirectPort" required="false">
      <p>If this <strong>Connector</strong> is supporting non-SSL
      requests, and a request is received for which a matching
      <code>&lt;security-constraint&gt;</code> requires SSL transport,
      Catalina will automatically redirect the request to the port
      number specified here.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="scheme" required="false">
      <p>Set this attribute to the name of the protocol you wish to have
      returned by calls to <code>request.getScheme()</code>.  For
      example, you would set this attribute to "<code>https</code>"
      for an SSL Connector.  The default value is "<code>http</code>".</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="secure" required="false">
      <p>Set this attribute to <code>true</code> if you wish to have
      calls to <code>request.isSecure()</code> to return <code>true</code>
      for requests received by this Connector (you would want this on an
      SSL Connector).  The default value is <code>false</code>.</p>
    </attribute>

  </attributes>

  <p><strong>FIXME</strong> - Update the above descriptions for anything
  that the WARP Connector delegates to Apache.</p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Standard Implementation">

  <p>The standard implementation of <strong>Webapp Connector</strong> is
  <strong>org.apache.catalina.connector.warp.WarpConnector</strong>.
  It supports the following additional attributes (in addition to the
  common attributes listed above):</p>

  <attributes>

    <attribute name="acceptCount" required="false">
      <p>The maximum queue length for incoming connection requests when
      all possible request processing threads are in use.  Any requests
      received when the queue is full will be refused.  The default
      value is 10.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="debug" required="false">
      <p>The debugging detail level of log messages generated by this
      component, with higher numbers creating more detailed output.
      If not specified, this attribute is set to zero (0).</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="maxProcessors" required="false">
      <p>The maximum number of request processing threads to be created
      by this <strong>Connector</strong>, which therefore determines the
      maximum number of simultaneous requests that can be handled.  If
      not specified, this attribute is set to 20.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="minProcessors" required="false">
      <p>The number of request processing threads that will be created
      when this <strong>Connector</strong> is first started.  This
      attribute should be set to a value smaller than that set for
      <code>maxProcessors</code>.  The default value is 5.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="port" required="true">
      <p>The TCP port number on which this <strong>Connector</strong>
      will create a server socket and await incoming connections.  Your
      operating system will allow only one server application to listen
      to a particular port number on a particular IP address.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="appBase" required="false">
      <p>Set the applications base directory for <strong>Hosts </strong>
      created via WARP.
      The default value is "webapps".</p>
    </attribute>

  </attributes>

  </subsection>

</section>


<section name="Nested Components">

  <subsection name="WarpEngine">
  
  <p>mod-webapp offers a specific Engine when running the
  <strong>Webapp Connector</strong> in its own
  <a href="service.html">service</a>.
  This Engine allows webapp to create and to map the
  <a href="host.html">Hosts</a> corresponding to the VirtualHost defined in the
  httpd.conf file.</p>
  <p>The standard implementation of <strong>Webapp Engine</strong> is
  <strong>org.apache.catalina.connector.warp.WarpEngine</strong>.
  It supports the standard <a href="engine.html">Engine</a>.
  attributes. </p>

  </subsection>

</section>


<section name="Special Features">

  <p><strong>FIXME</strong> - Document any special features supported by the
  WARP Connector.</p>

</section>


</body>

</document>
